Finding Aid for Dan Sicko Papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dan Sicko Papers 1983-2008, 1993-2003
Sicko, Dan.
2.5 linear feet
2013035 Aa 2
The Dan Sicko Papers comprise the written work and research undertaken by Sicko on the topic of Detroit techno music and its significance for the broader techno genre. The collection's four series contain materials pertaining to Sicko's book Techno Rebels: The Renegades of Electronic Funk, articles written over the course of Sicko's career as a freelance music journalist, popular and scholarly articles written by others, industry-specific and general interest periodicals, and sound recordings of interviews with Detroit-based techno artists, producers, and distributors.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated to the library in 2012 by Ms. Amy Lobsiger (Donor No. 10870 )
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Daniel S. Sicko was a music journalist and scholar of techno music dedicated to legitimizing Detroit techno and establishing its place in music history. He earned a B.S. from the University of Detroit in 1990 and established a career in digital advertising, ultimately serving as a Creative Director of the Detroit office of the advertising firm Organic, Inc. Early in his career Sicko was a freelance writer for Rolling Stone, electronic and underground music periodicals such as Alternative Press and URB, and the digital technology magazine Wired. He also founded Reverb, one of the first periodicals exclusively devoted to digital music. Sicko is perhaps best known for his book Techno Rebels: The Renegades of Electronic Funk (first published in 1999 and reissued in 2010), which is widely considered to be a groundbreaking text with regard to the history of Detroit techno music. Techno Rebels chronicles the genre's origins as an underground movement led by Detroit's African-American high school students. Sicko also gave lectures on the Detroit music scene and was a key figure in the establishment of the 313 Mailing List (a 1990s mailing list critical for enthusiasts of Detroit techno). Throughout his career Sicko engaged in extensive researches on the Detroit music industry and on electronic music in general, for which he conducted dozens of interviews with Detroit-based techno artists and producers. He died of ocular melanoma on August 28th, 2011 at the age of 42.
Source: Kirn, Peter. "Loss of a Techno Rebel: Why Dan Sicko will be Sorely Missed." createdigitalmusic.com, 29 August 2011.
The Dan Sicko Papers comprise over two decades of Sicko's writings and research materials pertaining to the history of Detroit techno music and its role in the electronic music industry. The collection is divided into four series: Writings, Research Materials, Periodicals, and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Sicko, Dan.; Music journalists--Michigan--Detroit.; Musicians--Michigan--Detroit--Interviews.; Techno music--History.; Techno rebels: the renegades of electronic funk.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Musicians--Michigan--Detroit--Interviews.; Techno music--History.
Genre Terms:
Microcassettes.; CD-ROMs.; Photographs.
- Writings
  The Writings series is divided into three subseries: Techno Rebels: The Renegades of Electronic Funk (book), Articles and Drafts, and Miscellaneous Papers. The first subseries is composed of materials pertaining to Sicko's book, including drafts, research materials, interview transcripts, and publication materials. The second subseries contains published articles and article drafts written by Sicko about Detroit techno for various electronic music publications (including Anti-Matter Magazine and URB). The last subseries contains miscellaneous correspondence, notes, and resumes.
  - Techno Rebels: the Renegades of Electronic Funk (book)
    - Galley proof 1999 (Box 1)
    - Complete draft (Box 1)
    - Annotated drafts, preface and chapter 1 (Box 1)
    - Digital copy (CD-ROM) (Box 1)
    - Book proposal (Box 1)
    - Publisher's Q & A (Box 1)
    - Notes and research (includes articles) 1990s (Box 1)
    - Interviews with Delano Smith, Derrick May, Alan Oldham, others (Box 1)
    - Edits (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (feedback and suggestions) 1995-1998, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Ephemera and images 1999 (Box 1)
    - Press releases and articles 1998-2000 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Drafts
    - "H-Gun Labs: Ammo for your Brain" 1996 (Box 1)
    - "H-Gun: 'it's all kind of blurry'" (Box 1)
    - "Home Bass: Detroit's Electro-Funk Slides into the Limelight" (drafts) (Box 1)
    - "Methodical Progression: Submerge Represents the new Face of Independent? Underground?" (Box 1)
    - "Ocean to Ocean: the Rise of the Techno Tourist" (draft) (Box 1)
    - "Techno: Detroit's Agents of Change" (Box 1)
    - Articles and reviews published in Anti-Matter Magazine, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Articles published in URB, Wired, 1994-1997 (Box 1)
    - Partial drafts and notes (Box 1)
    - Cranbrook Academy of Art lecture 2001 (Box 1)
      (given by Sicko, on the topic of Detroit's role in the development of techno)
  - Miscellaneous Papers
    - Correspondence (mostly email) 1997-1998, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence regarding Sicko's freelance writing 1995-1998 (Box 1)
    - Resumes (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1)
- Research Materials
  The Research Materials series is divided into three subseries, the first of which (Techno Music and the Music Industry) is comprised of newsletters, periodical articles, and press clippings on the topic of techno music and the electronic music industry in general. This subseries includes articles and research materials pertaining to rave culture, various audio formats, music videos, and international techno. The second subseries (Detroit Techno) contains researches that are specific to Detroit, including scholarly articles and papers, newspaper clippings, and ephemera pertaining to the Detroit techno scene, Detroit music history, and urban renewal. This subseries also contains materials from the Detroit Electronic Music Festival and the Shrinking Cities Project (the latter of which includes Sicko's paper on the Detroit music scene). The third subseries (Musical Artists and Producers) is composed of materials pertaining to individual techno artists, production companies, and record labels (many of them Detroit-based), including biographies, periodical and newspaper clippings, photographs, discographies, press releases, and album reviews. This subseries also includes several interview transcripts and accompanying drafts of articles.
  - Techno Music and the Music Industry
    - Anti-Matter Magazine, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Clear Newsletter, press releases and reviews (includes correspondence), 1995-1998 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters (including Brand-X, GTP (Global Techno Power), Fast Forward, Energy Flash, Under One Sky, Fuzzy Paradise, Low Res, Sublime the Paper), 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Assorted articles pertaining to techno music 1997 (Box 1)
    - Clippings from mainstream periodicals pertaining to techno music (including Time Out, Details), 1993-1997 (Box 1)
    - Article about electronica (XLR8R,) 2008 (Box 1)
    - Articles about rave culture 1995-1999 (Box 1)
    - Altered State: the Story of Ecstasy Culture and Acid House, by Matthew Collin (book reviews), 1997 (Box 1)
    - H-Gun Labs (music video production company), assorted articles 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - H-Gun Labs, filmography (Box 1)
    - Articles about the MiniDisc audio format 1999 (Box 1)
    - Article about vinyl records 1997 (Box 1)
    - Future Music Festival (includes Sicko's article "Japan Looks to the Future of Music") (1999) (Box 1)
    - London techno scene, assorted articles 1994-1999 (Box 1)
    - Email correspondence on the topic of the international techno scene (Belgium, Estonia, Finland, Japan, the Netherlands, the United Kingdom) 1998 (Box 1)
    - Modulations (film project pertaining to the history of electronic music) 1998 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Techno
    - Shrinking Cities Project
      - "Bubble Metropolis: Expanding Detroit's Identity Through Music" (Sicko) 2003 (Box 1)
      - Detroit (report) 2004 (Box 1)
      - Music exhibition (notes, itineraries, ephemera) 2003 (Box 1)
      - Articles about urban underground music 2003 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Electronic Music Festival (includes itinerary, artist list, press release, ephemera) 2000-2001 (Box 1)
    - "Detroit Techno" (undergraduate history thesis by Ben Tausig) (Box 1)
    - "Can't Forget the Motor City": Creem Magazine, Rock Music, Detroit Identity, Mass Consumerism, and Counterculture" by Michael J. Kramer, 2002 (Box 1)
      (article published in the Michigan Historical Review)
    - "The Constructivist Moment: From El Lissitzsky to Detroit Techno" by Barrett Watten, 1997 (Box 1)
      article published in Qui Parle)
    - Proposal for an unspecified paper about Detroit techno (Box 1)
    - Pamphlets and ephemera pertaining to the Detroit techno scene (artists, DJs, events) 1990s-2000s (Box 1)
    - Assorted Detroit newspaper articles pertaining to Detroit techno 1989-1999 (Box 1)
    - Detroit music scene, assorted articles 1983-2003 (Box 1)
    - Research pertaining to urban renewal in Detroit 1997 (Box 1)
  - Musical Artists and Producers
    - Adult. (Detroit music duo) (publicity materials, album reviews, articles) 2001 (Box 1)
    - AUX 88 (Detroit-based electronic music group) 1996 (Box 1)
    - Underground Resistance (Detroit techno music collective) 1996 (Box 1)
    - Biographies of individual artists (including Squarepusher, Brainbox, Ultramarine, Carl Craig) 1990s-2002 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings (photocopies) regarding individual artists (including Cybotron, Inner City, Juan Atkins, Alan Oldham) 1987-1989, 1991-1994, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Photographs of individual artists (black and white, likely used as illustrations for Techno Rebels) (Box 1)
    - Discographies (Bjork, Plaid, Underground Resistance, Metroplex label) 1985-1997 (Box 1)
    - Billboard Charts, lists of singles 1985-1990s (Box 1)
    - Track listings, assorted artists (Box 1)
    - Press releases for albums to be reviewed (record labels include Delsin Records, Emoticon, deFocus) 1994-1995, 2000-2004 (Box 1)
    - Music distributors (Box 1)
    - Interviews
      - Mike Archer, of the Archer Record Processing Plant (Box 1)
        (includes partial drafts for an article entitled "Spin Cycle")
      - Juan Atkins (Box 1)
        (includes partial draft for Sicko's article "Juan Atkins: Techno Comes of Age")
      - dbx (audio recording equipment company) (Box 1)
      - Goldie (Box 1)
        (includes article, discography, and partial draft for Sicko's article "Joyriding Technology: Goldie and the Evolution of Urban Music")
      - H-Gun Labs (music video production company) (Box 1)
        (likely for an article entitled "the Beauty of Decay")
      - Ron Murphy, of Sound Enterprises (Box 1)
      - Submerge (distributor for Detroit electronic music) (Box 1)
      - Sam Valenti (DJ and founder of record label Ghostly International) (Box 1)
      - Interview transcripts (unspecified interviewees) (Box 1)
- Periodicals
  The Periodicals series contains several dozen periodicals arranged in alphabetical order by title. These include both mainstream and music industry periodicals, some relatively obscure. The publications in this series are devoted to such topics as techno and electronic music, underground or avant-garde music scenes, the entertainment industry, urban culture, and the city of Detroit. Some include articles contributed by Sicko. The majority are English-language periodicals from the 1990s, among which RES, URB, and The Wire are best represented. Oversized periodicals are listed and housed separately.
  - A.P. (Alternative Press) (Box 2)
    - 49 July 1992 (Box 2)
  - Blaster
    - February 1995 (Box 2)
    - March 1995 (Box 2)
  - Details
    - July 1992 (the music issue) (Box 2)
  - Detroit Monthly
    - June 1993 (Box 2)
  - ele-king
    - Vol. 26 August-September 1999 (Box 2)
  - The Face
    - No. 11 August 1989 (Box 2)
    - No. 55 April 1993 (Box 2)
    - No. 13 February 1998 (Box 2)
  - The Fader
    - No. 6 Winter 2000 (Box 2)
  - Future Music
    - No. 6 April 1993 (Box 2)
  - Giant Robot
    - No. 12 (Box 2)
    - No. 17 (Box 2)
  - Hour Detroit
    - November 1997 (Box 2)
    - November 1998 (Box 2)
  - i-D
    - No. 137 February 1995 (Box 2)
  - Mix Mag
    - No. 90 July 1990 (Box 2)
  - Muzik
    - No. 16 September 1996 (Box 2)
    - No. 22 March 1997 (Box 2)
    - No. 31 December 1997 (Box 2)
  - The New Yorker
    - August 26, 1996, September 2, 1996 (music issue) (Box 2)
  - Orbit
    - August 1999 (Box 2)
    - Fall 1999 (final issue) (Box 2)
  - Prototype
    - Vol. 1 No. 1 October 1989 (Box 2)
  - RES
    - Summer preview issue 1997 (Box 2)
    - Festival preview issue (Box 2)
    - Vol. 2 No. 2 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 2 No. 3 (Box 2)
    - No. 3 Spring 1998 (Box 2)
  - Straight no Chaser
    - Vol. 2 No. 5 Summer 1999 (Box 2)
  - Sweater
    - December 1997-January 1998 (Box 2)
  - Vogue
    - January 1992 (Box 2)
  - The Wire
    - 131 January 1995 (Box 2)
    - 140 October 1995 (Box 2)
    - 141 November 1995 (Box 2)
    - 150, August 1996 (Box 2)
    - 159 May 1997 (Box 2)
    - 161 July 1997 (Box 2)
    - 162 August 1997 (Box 2)
    - 169 March 1998 (Box 2)
  - XLR8R
    - 60 July-August 2002 (Box 2)
  - Oversized Periodicals (Box 3)
    - Billboard
      - July 3, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Ray Gun
      - No. 72 October 1999 (Box 3)
    - URB
      - 25 February-March 1993 (Box 3)
      - 26 March-April 1993 (Box 3)
      - 27 April-May 1993 (Box 3)
      - 32, November 1993 (Box 3)
      - 33 December 1993-January 1994 (Box 3)
      - 34 February 1994 (Box 3)
      - 35 April 1994 (Box 3)
      - 36 June 1994 (Box 3)
      - 39 November 1994 (Box 3)
      - 47 April 1996 (Box 3)
      - 49 July 1996 (Box 3)
      - 50 August-September 1996 (Box 3)
      - 52 January-February 1997 (Box 3)
      - Vol. 11 No. 87, September 2001 (Box 3)
- Sound Recordings
  The Sound Recordings series contains a total of 36 microcassette tapes which likely consist predominantly of recordings of interviews Sicko conducted with Detroit-based techno artists, producers, and others active in the Detroit electronic music industry. Many of these interviews were likely undertaken for Sicko's book Techno Rebels: The Renegades of Electronic Funk. N.B.: microcassette labeling is occasionally inconsistent or illegible.
  - Group 1, 22 audiocassettes microcassettes
    - Schrierbach (Box 3)
    - H-Gun Labs 1996 (Box 3)
    - Derrick/Matt (Box 3)
    - Tim Meadows I (Box 3)
    - Tim Meadows II (Box 3)
    - Jonah Sharp (Box 3)
    - Jamie Hodge (Box 3)
    - Morgan Geist (Box 3)
    - Detroit Bass (Box 3)
    - Plaid (Box 3)
    - H-Gun (Box 3)
    - H-Gun II (Box 3)
    - Todd Johnson (Box 3)
    - Consolidated 1992 (Box 3)
    - Drexciya (Box 3)
    - MBM/NYO (Box 3)
    - Thonton (?) (Box 3)
    - Roland (Box 3)
    - Claude (Box 3)
    - KMS/Eddie (Box 3)
    - Mad Mike (Box 3)
    - DW (Box 3)
    - Peter Wohelski (empty case) (Box 3)
    - 90's Channel/Cybersonik (empty case) (Box 3)
  - Group 2, 14 audiocassettes microcassettes
    - DRX/Pat Milly, Kevin O'Neill (Box 3)
    - Peter Wohelski (Box 3)
    - Speedy J. (Box 3)
    - Archer/Ron Murphy (Box 3)
    - Joe Archer (Box 3)
    - Shake (Box 3)
    - Alan Oldham (Box 3)
    - Ferenc (Box 3)
    - Richie Hawtin (Box 3)
    - 808 State (Box 3)
    - Delano (Box 3)
    - Neil Rushton (Box 3)
    - Todd Johnson (Box 3)
    - TJ (Box 3)